There are numerous knowledge points about open-source large models
Today we've invited Kuntai to explain MOE to everyone
Well, if I had to summarize it in one sentence
The purpose of the ME model is actually quite simple
it aims to use the same computational resources
to train a much larger model, uh
First of all, the MOE model
translated into Chinese as the mixture of experts model
Want to know why we need to train a mixture of experts model?
Let's travel back to the era before the mixture of experts model
Suppose we are now large model trainers
Uh
The goal is to utilize the existing computational resources
train a model that is significantly smarter than existing models
shock the world with China
So how exactly should we do it?
At that time, there were roughly two widely recognized laws about large models.
The first law is called the model's skin law
which means that for every order of magnitude increase in model scale
the model may become slightly smarter
So the second, the second rule is that the computational requirements of the model
is roughly proportional to the number of model parameters
So this makes you think, right?
your intelligence
You need more parameters to make the model smarter
and more parameters mean more computational resources
Therefore, greater intelligence equals more computational resources.
So without purchasing more GPUs, we can't train smarter models
Oh, then we're stuck here, aren't we?
We only have so many GPUs
What should we do if we want to train a smarter model?
So is there any way we can break through this dilemma?
Yes, the solution is to design sparse architectures
find ways to increase the model scale while
without increasing the computational cost of the model
In that case
we can use the same number of GPUs
train a much larger model
Okay, so the next question is
How do we construct this sparsity?
Let's start with a brief introduction to the basic architecture of large models
is the transformers architecture
This architecture consists of a series of Transformer modules
stacked together like building blocks
There are just two modules in each block
the attention module and the feed-forward network module
The attention module is responsible for establishing
the interrelationships between words
while the feedforward network module performs in-depth understanding of the words themselves
For large models
feed-forward network module
that is, the number of parameters for this deep understanding of the words themselves
accounts for about 80% of the entire model
That is to say
as long as we can make this feedforward network module ten times more efficient
then with the same computational budget
the number of parameter models can roughly double to eight times the original wow
That's awesome
If we can use the same amount of model computational resources
train a model eight times larger
This is definitely going to shock the tech industry. Okay
So our goal is set
We want to sparsify the feedforward network modules
for example, sparsify it by tenfold
So how exactly do we do it?
The simplest approach is a two-step process
First, divide the parameters in the feedforward network module
evenly divide the parameters of each layer into ten parts
then create a selector
select one parameter from the ten partitions to execute
So if you also think this way
You're so smart
You've already designed it
The pioneer of mixture-of-experts models is called Switch Transformers
This is an extremely simplified version of the mixture of experts model.
Each set of parameters we mentioned earlier is called an expert.
So this approach of selecting one expert per layer
Can it be further optimized?
Of course it can
The core flaw of this approach
As you might imagine, some relatively general capabilities
for example, understanding the semantics of a sentence
is a capability required to solve many problems
So if only one expert is working at each layer,
This means
regardless of the expert
more or less forced to learn these generic capabilities
What a waste that is!
Different experts could have learned completely different things.
yet they end up being forced to learn these same generic capabilities
So we might as well do it this way
let some experts specialize in learning general capabilities
and then add some other experts
on the foundation of general capabilities
drawing strengths from various specialized domains
blossoming everywhere
Congratulations
You've just designed the two core technologies of Deep SG MoE
The first technique is the shared expert
which refers to the experts shared by all requests
We use it to learn general capabilities
The second technique is fine-grained experts
make the granularity of experts finer
thereby expanding the number of experts
blossom everywhere
So the trainers happily used the technology provided by Deep SME
sparsified the feedforward network module by a factor of ten
happily ran the training script
So what happened as a result?
Uh, the training suddenly crashed.
Millions of yuan went up in smoke.
promotions and salary increases are gone
or even lose their jobs
So why does the training crash?
This is actually because
The training process of the mixture of experts model is highly unstable.
Let's adopt the perspective of the expert selection module
Let's understand why this is the case
Let's say we are in a company
individual responsible for routing requests to experts
Then you realize that
Although all experts work at the same speed
but there are just a few experts whose capabilities grow very slowly
then gradually the output quality of these experts will become increasingly lower
then naturally we will gradually
assign tasks to others
After all, if the final output efficiency is poor
we ourselves would also be held accountable
then ultimately these weak experts become weaker and weaker
the less work they get
The less work they get, the weaker they become
eventually become the weakest experts
the overall intelligence of the entire model goes offline
In other words, the above process
is due to the training phase
the routing module aims to optimize model performance
while allocating all the training load to the stronger experts
resulting in weaker experts being increasingly less likely to be selected by the routing module
it becomes increasingly difficult to receive training workload
eventually stops learning
the overall intelligence of the model goes offline
So to solve this problem
The key is to design a mechanism
to balance the training load among different experts as evenly as possible
Well, this is actually a very deep topic
I won't go into detail
If you want to follow up on the research papers
STMOE and the lostfree balancing in the deep sic series of papers
free balancing is a great starting point
So let's assume that the model trainers have gone through all the hardships
finally solved the model's stability issues
They happily handed the model over to the inference engineers
and boasted
Oh
My model can achieve the same performance with just 1/10 of the computational resources
achieve the same performance as the largest model
Then the model trainer got very excited
ran a test
found it was completely not the case
This inference process is excruciatingly slow
not to mention ten times
twice the speed might even be a stretch
Why is the inference process so slow?
This is because the mixture of experts model is less friendly to the inference process
The reason is that during the training process
a large number of inputs are dumped into the model all at once
basically all experts will be assigned tasks
so reading one expert's weights can serve many tokens
very cost-effective
However, during the training process
especially during the decoding stage
each request generates only one new token at a time
Therefore, each request only activates a few experts per layer.
This situation frequently occurs
I read all the weights of one expert
resulting in only serving one token in this scenario
This results in the model spending most of its inference time
is spent on reading expert weights
rather than on actual computation
So the efficiency naturally drops.
To solve this problem
We need to optimize the inference engine
to improve inference performance
These optimizations primarily serve three core purposes
The first objective is to improve operator efficiency
the core open-source libraries
for example, DB Station
DBEP and the GPU kernel written by perplexity
The second core technology is the parallelization of communication and computation.
This optimization leverages the underlying mechanism of the graphics card.
As long as you can provide the graphics card with both communication load and computation load simultaneously
then the GPU can simultaneously perform computation and communication without interference
The core technique of this method is primarily dual batch overlap
Dual batch overlap
Figuratively speaking,
is to have two sets of requests alternate like a ping-pong game
switching back and forth between the inference and computation processes of large models
thereby ensuring as much as possible that within the same time period
there is computational load from one set of requests
while communication load comes from another set of requests
In this way
we may we can achieve as much as possible
simultaneously utilizing the hardware's computational and communication capabilities
Third, try to enable large-scale parallel processing of the same model as much as possible
then distribute across multiple cards to serve more requests
This representative method is called large-scale expert parallelism
also known as white expert parallel y's batch
The core of this technique is
to distribute the experts in the expert model across different GPUs
this way the entire model occupies more GPUs
can therefore handle higher loads
on average, the number of requests each expert receives increases
then reading the expert weights once can serve multiple requests
the efficiency is thus improved
At the same time, because the model is distributed across multiple GPUs
then the GPU memory usage of the model is reduced
more space is reserved for the kv cache
the inference batch size can be further increased
thereby further increasing the throughput
So you see, starting from saving computational power in the beginning
to the intermediate load balancing
to the final race for speed
the evolution of Mixture of Experts models
is essentially within limited resources
especially under the constraints of limited GPU resources
model trainers and inference engineers rack their brains
outsmarting the graphics cards
the history of squeezing every last bit of computing power
A very brilliant explanation
Thank you for the bandwidth
Thank you for the invitation, uncle